<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on The proposal for sending back the nobility and gentry of Ireland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3199A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11922821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11922821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on The proposal for sending back the nobility and gentry of Ireland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tim. Goodwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Lately printed" on last leaf indicates the author of "The proposal for sending back the nobility and gentry of Ireland" as Richard Buckley.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckley, Richard, --  Sir. --  Proposal for sending back the nobility and gentry of Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50986:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50986:1"/>
            <p>Animadverſions ON THE PROPOSAL FOR SENDING BACK THE NOBILITY and GENTRY OF IRELAND.</p>
            <p>LICENS'D <hi>January</hi> 1. 1689/90.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tim. Goodwin,</hi> at the <hi>Maiden-head</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50986:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50986:2"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS ON THE Propoſal for Sending Back THE Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WAlking the other day in the Court of Requeſts (near to the <hi>Areopagus</hi> of <hi>London, where moſt men ſpend their time in nothing elſe, but either to tell, or to hear ſome new thing),</hi> I encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd a Pamphlet, dreſs'd up in the new Mode of <hi>A Letter to a Gentleman,</hi> and ſtiling it ſelf, <hi>The Propoſal for ſending back the Nobility and Gentry of</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I began to think with my ſelf, what pity it is, that now (when by a War with <hi>France,</hi> and the Inhibition of all Trade and Commerce from thence, the Commodities of that Countrey are grown ſcarce and dear) ſo much Paper ſhould be waſted in ſuch idle and unprofitable Trifles. If any Anſwer be made to this (thought I) there muſt be more Paper miſ-imploy'd; if it paſs without Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Author will be confirmed in the opinion of his own Sufficiency, and be tempted to expoſe more ſuch unlick'd Lumps to the amuſement of the Vulgar. Thereupon I ſate down to read it, and was not at all deceiv'd in my expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for I found it to be a bold, and moſt diſobliging Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a moſt irrational and impracticable Project, and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated by a very diſ-ingenuous humour of Perſonal Scandals and Reflections. But, to obviate all ſuſpicion of Prejudice or Paſſion, I will take the Engine in pieces, and handle every Wheel and Joint of it, and then ſubmit to every impartial Reader, whether <hi>R. B</hi> who ſubſcribes the Letter, hath proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any tolerable candor, or diſcretion. But I deſire to be rightly underſtood: I do not undertake this Task, to make an Anſwer to the Parts of his Propoſal and Scheme; that is done throughly and ſufficiently by the Anſwer given in to the Lords of the Committee, and I ſhall expoſe it anon: I deſign this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50986:3"/>only to animadvert on the frivolous Cavils and Conundrums ventilated by the Author of the <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt (looking as big as <hi>Hudibras</hi> himſelf) he enters the Liſts, with a bold defiance, That <hi>ſome of his Countrey-men dare not put their Honeſty in the Ballance with His.</hi> I cannot judge of what I do not know; things immaterial and inviſible can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be cramm'd into a Scale; and ſo dare not take upon me to be the Arbitrator. But ſurely his <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> may juſtly be <hi>call'd in queſtion,</hi> who has ſo manifeſtly prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in his Projections, and obtruded upon the World <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals</hi> and <hi>Schemes</hi> ſo apparently and materially differing from thoſe he preſented to the Council, and to the Committee. And (that I may uſe his words) <hi>to demonſtrate both, my firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Argument ſhall be to produce</hi> the written as well as the printed <hi>Propoſals,</hi> that ſo every individual perſon may obſerve their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfering and contradiction.</p>
            <div type="proposal">
               <head>The Propoſal preſented to His Majeſty, and by the Lords of the Council communicated to the Committee.</head>
               <p>AFter the laſt Rebellion in <hi>Ireland, through the want of Tillage,</hi> there followed a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; and the <hi>heaps</hi> of thoſe who dy'd of Famine, caus'd a Plague; ſo that many more dy'd by <hi>Famine</hi> and <hi>Plague,</hi> than by the <hi>War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame thing may be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed now, there being little or no Tillage for the next year; and the common <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who liv'd moſt upon their Potato-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, being now in the Army, do conſume five times more Corn than they did when they lived at home in their Cabbins; by which means the great Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50986:3"/>had this year, will be eaten up before the next; ſo that tho that Kingdom ſhould be intirely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the next Summer, yet the want of Bread will make it Deſolate; for the late King's braſs Money, having eaten up all the Silver in that Kingdom, there is no Money left to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Corn abroad, ſo that the People muſt unavoidably dye for want of Bread.</p>
               <p>There is now near one half of that Kingdom reduced, and yet the Proteſtants even of that part, are moſt of them ſtill in <hi>England;</hi> the Conſequence of <hi>their</hi> ſtay here, muſt be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine there: For the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are almoſt all taken up in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the late King, and thoſe who are not, will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, neither Plough nor Sow, where they know not their Landlords; ſo that while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtay here, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Farmers fly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Army, there it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the more Your Majeſtys Army ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, the more muſt that Kingdom become waſte; but if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are now here, were in that part of the Kingdom, which is now reduced, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> who now fly before our Army, would come in and gladly ſettle again <hi>under their old Maſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50986:4"/>
               <p>Your Majeſty has a fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to oblige the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that ſtay here to return, by the Addreſs which the Houſe of Commons made to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in their behalf, <hi>for ſome relief for them.</hi> Now, if Your Majeſty were pleaſed <hi>to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into</hi> Ireland, <hi>whatever Your Majeſty is graciouſly pleaſed to give them, excepting only what would bear their Charges thither, and order it to be there paid,</hi> with obligation on every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who receives any of it, to Sow <hi>ſuch a</hi> proportion of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-corn (which may be done in <hi>March</hi> next) it will be the only means to prevent a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; and moreover, ſuch numbers returning, would be a Terror to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and an Encouragement to the <hi>Labouring Husbandman</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, who is now fled, and who had rather be at the Plough, than at the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50986:4"/>
               <p>Such of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as have their own Eſtates to go to, have no reaſon to expect <hi>equal ſhare of Money</hi> with thoſe, whoſe Eſtates are yet under the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and <hi>that which is abated, or deducted from them, who can enjoy their own Eſtates,</hi> will be a conſiderable Addition, the better to enable thoſe, whoſe Eſtates are yet unconquered, to ſettle for <hi>their</hi> preſent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence <hi>on the Lands that are forfeited to Your Majeſty, which Lands will be thereby kept in a profitable Condition, to be given up as ſoon as theſe Men are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their own Eſtates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this will be a competent Proviſion for the Nobility and Gentry, ſo that which is yet remaining of the Collect-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, may be for the poorer ſort; which being paid them at one entire ſum, would be an help to ſettle them under the Gentry, to become Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, as they were formerly; and if they plow but little, yet their being in the Countrey will be an Encouragement for others to go over.</p>
               <p>If Your Majeſty be pleaſed to order that this Collect Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney alſo may be diſtributed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> it will then be ſeen who are real Objects of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and the Money will be laid out to a good uſe, <hi>and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>not to feed the Luxuriouſneſs and Idleneſs of ſome here (as too much of it does now)</hi> it is to be fear'd that all will not go over, who yet complain now that they have not whereon to live.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Houſe of Commons did humbly addreſs to Your Majeſty for to lay down for our Relief</hi> 15000 <hi>li. (that being a fourth part of what they were pleaſed to rate for a years Allowance for us) they promiſing to ſee Your Majeſty repaid. That Sum is indeed much too ſmall to effect this Undertaking; but if Your Majeſty were graciouſly pleas'd to make it the whole</hi> 60000 <hi>li. It would do greater things than I have yet mentioned; and would ſend away a multitude of People, whoſe wants make them very importunate and troubleſome here; and it would be a means both of ſaving the Kingdom, and alſo the Lives of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Perſons in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is of as great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſpeedily to Plant that Kingdom, as to Reduce it; and perhaps 60000 <hi>l.</hi> may do that now, which cannot be done the next year with <hi>thrice</hi> that ſum; while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtay here, it cannot <hi>reaſonably</hi> be ſuppoſed that Strangers will go thither. <hi>And the</hi> Iriſh <hi>who are fed with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes from the</hi> French, <hi>will believe them when they ſee the</hi> Engliſh <hi>ſo fearful to return.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all ſuch as are a Clamour and a Charge to</hi> England, <hi>may have this Money, for going to</hi> Ireland <hi>to receive,</hi> then all thoſe who will not go over, will be left without excuſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> if this Money be not ſent over now, and the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> ſent away to Sow Corn there, a greater ſum than now pays the Army, will not be ſufficient the next year to keep the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> in that Kingdom with Bread. And the Proſpect is yet more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble if we conſider, That when ever Corn was dear in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> we always ſetch'd it from <hi>France;</hi> but now we muſt go ſeek other Markets, which cannot be done without vaſt expence, ſince this general War through <hi>Europe</hi> will take up ſo much Corn for all the Armies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have laid down in another Paper, a Scheme, or Method to ſhew that all this is very eaſie to be practiſed; and I have alſo lay'd down ſome other great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of it, beſides what are here before-mentioned.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="proposal">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50986:3"/>
               <head>The Propoſal, as it is Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</head>
               <p>AFter the laſt Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there followed a Famine; and the <hi>Carcaſſes</hi> of thoſe who died of Famine, cauſed a Plague; ſo that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more dy'd by <hi>Famine</hi> and <hi>Plague,</hi> than by the <hi>War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame thing may be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed now, there being little or no Tillage for the next year; and the common <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who liv'd moſt upon their Potato-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, being now in the Army, do conſume ten times more Corn than they did when they lived at home in their Cabbins; by which means that great har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50986:3"/>had this year, will be eaten up before the next; ſo that altho that Kingdom ſhould be entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reduced the next Summer, yet the want of Bread will make it Deſolate; for the late King's braſs Money, having ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten up all the Silver of that Kingdom, there is no Money left to purchaſe Corn abroad, ſo that the People muſt una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably die for want of Bread.</p>
               <p>There is now near one half of that Kingdom reduced, and yet the Proteſtants, even of that part, are moſt of them ſtill in <hi>England;</hi> the Conſequence of <hi>whoſe</hi> ſtay here, muſt be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine there. For the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are almoſt all of them taken up in the Service of the late King, and thoſe who are not, will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, neither Plough nor Sow, when they know not their Landlord; ſo that while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtay here, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Farmers fly before our Army there, it muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, that the more Your Majeſties Army advances, the more muſt that Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come waſte; but if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are now here, were in that part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which is reduced, <hi>then</hi> the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who now fly before our Army, would come in, and gladly ſettle again <hi>on their old Farms, when they have ſome body to protect them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50986:4"/>
               <p>Your Majeſty has a fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to oblige the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that ſtay here, to return, by the Addreſs which the Houſe of Commons made to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in their behalf, <hi>For one fourth part of a years Allowance, which in the whole did amount to</hi> 60000 <hi>l.</hi> Now, if Your Majeſty were <hi>graciouſly</hi> pleaſed <hi>to give them here the Sum of</hi> 15000 <hi>l. being a fourth part thereof; and to tranſmit into</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>the Sum of</hi> 45000 <hi>l. more to be there paid to ſuch of them, as will go over,</hi> with Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on every Perſon, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives any of it, to Sow <hi>a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> proportion of Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn, (which may <hi>yet</hi> be done in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April</hi> next) it will be the only means to prevent a Famine; <hi>it would ſend</hi> away a multitude of People, whoſe <hi>wants make them importunate here, and would in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſupply thoſe wants.</hi> And moreover, ſuch numbers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, would be a Terror to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, and an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the <hi>Iriſh La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer and Husbandman</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, who are now fled, and who had rather be at Plough, than at the Musket. <hi>Whereas now, the</hi> Iriſh <hi>who are fed with Promiſes from the</hi> French; <hi>will believe them, and be thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, when they ſee the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>ſo fearful to return.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50986:4"/>
               <p>Such of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as have their own Eſtates to go to, have no reaſon to expect <hi>to be under the ſame Conditions</hi> with thoſe whoſe Eſtates are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Enemy; <hi>and that Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made between them,</hi> will be a conſiderable addition, the better to enable thoſe whoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates are yet unconquered, to ſettle for <hi>a</hi> preſent ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, <hi>on ſuch little Farms as their Circumſtances will allow of, whereby they may get a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Stock of their own, againſt they remove to their own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: This will be a great help to thoſe of the</hi> North, <hi>who have Land to ſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this will be a competent Proviſion for the Nobility and Gentry, ſo that which is yet remaining of the Collect-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney may be for the poorer ſort; which being paid to them at one entire ſum, would be a help to ſettle them under the Gentry to become Tenants as they were formerly: and if they plow but little, yet their being in the Countrey will be an Encouragement for others to go over.</p>
               <p>If Your Majeſty be pleaſed to order that this Collect-Money alſo may be diſtributed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> it will then be ſeen who are Objects of Charity, and the Money will be laid out to a good uſe. It is to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>fear'd that all will not go over, who yet complain now that they have not whereon to live.</p>
               <p>It is of as great Conſequence ſpeedily to Plant that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as to Reduce it, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps 60000 <hi>l.</hi> may do that now, which cannot be done the next year with <hi>Ten times</hi> that Sum; <hi>and</hi> while the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtay here, it cannot be ſuppoſed that Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers will go thither <hi>to Plant.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>If this Money be ſent into</hi> Ireland, <hi>to be there given to ſuch as will go for it,</hi> then thoſe who will not go over, will be lef;t without excuſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> if this Money be not now ſent over, and the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> ſent away to Sow Corn there, a greater Sum than now pays the Army, will not be ſufficient the next year to keep the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> in that Kingdom with Bread. And the Proſpect is yet more terrible, if we conſider, that when ever Corn was dear in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fetched it from <hi>France;</hi> but now we muſt go ſeek other Markets, which cannot now be done without vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, ſince this general War throughout <hi>Europe</hi> will take up ſo much Corn for all the <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="scheme">
               <head>The firſt Scheme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in by the Projector.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is humbly propoſed that the King would <hi>be pleaſed</hi> to cauſe it to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>be made known <hi>publickly,</hi> That all the Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who now are in <hi>England,</hi> and whoſe uſual abode has been in <hi>Ireland,</hi> do forthwith return to that <hi>part</hi> of the Kingdom which is under His Majeſty's Authority, <hi>under pain of His Majeſty's diſpleaſure,</hi> except ſuch whom His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly order to ſtay here for His ſervice. And that for their Encouragement ſo to do, it is humbly propoſed,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, That His Majeſty would be Graciouſly pleaſed to give to <hi>all</hi> his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects of <hi>Ireland, whoſe Eſtates have been returned in to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and by them Rated,</hi> the Sum of 15000 <hi>l. to be paid them here, and that he would be graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed to ſend into</hi> Ireland <hi>the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſum of</hi> 45000 <hi>l.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>Stir.</hi> to be there diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to ſuch of them as will go over to that part of the Kingdom which is already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and there Sow Summer-Corn <hi>on their Eſtates (if they be of that Countrey) or on ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the</hi> Iriſh, <hi>as the Commiſſioners to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe ſhall aſſign to them, if their own Eſtates be in the Enemies poſſeſſion; and the ſaid</hi> 45000 <hi>l.</hi> be put into the hands of 2 ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, wealthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>of clear and unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Eſtates,</hi> Men of known Integrity; and that are not Dealers in Money, who may be Treaſurers of the ſame, they giving ſufficient and undoubted Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the payment of <hi>the ſaid</hi> 45000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in ſuch manner as is hereafter lay'd down, and that without any Fees or other Charges to be paid by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are to receive it.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>
               <p n="3">3dly, That His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would be pleaſed to nominate a number of Commiſſioners of the Nobility and Gentry of the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who knew all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that lye among theirs; and that thoſe Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may have Authority to ſet out and aſſign the Eſtates of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> as are willing to Sow Summer-Corn thereon for this next year only, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon whoſe ſhare of the ſaid Money ſhall amount to 20 <hi>l. or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> ſhall give Bond to the ſaid Treaſurer in the King's Name, to the value of what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, That for every 10 <hi>l.</hi> which he ſhall receive, he will Sow, if he be on his own Eſtate, Four Acres of <hi>Oats, Barley,</hi> or <hi>Peaſe.</hi> Upon his giving of theſe Bonds, the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners ſhall give him an Order to receive his ſhare of Money from the Treaſurers; <hi>and alſo a Writing of Aſſignment of the Lands, on which he is to Sow his Corn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4thly, For the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all ſuch to go over, whoſe Eſtates are yet <hi>in the Enemies Poſſeſſion,</hi> that they <hi>may</hi> be obliged to ſow but 2 Acres for every 10 <hi>li.</hi> that they ſhall receive, becauſe of the neceſſity that they will lie under
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>
                  <hi>of building for themſelves ſome convenient dwelling</hi> upon Land which is not their own.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the ſaid Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, or one of them, ſhall <hi>take care,</hi> that every perſon do ſow as much Corn as by Bond he was obliged to do; and that the ſame be not negligently thrown into the ground, only to eſcape the Penalty of the Bond; and therefore that at Harveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the ſaid Treaſurers, <hi>or one of them,</hi> ſhall ride about to ſee the ſame reaped; and that the Bonds ſhall be in force againſt all thoſe who have not their ſhare of Corn to reap, tho they did before anſwer the Obligation of their Bond by Sowing. By this means, His Majeſty's fatherly Care of His People will moſt evidently appear, in contriving that his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects there ſhall have at leaſt 10000 Acres of Corn the next year; whereas with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, there will not be an handful in the whole Kingdom, and thouſands muſt die for want of Bread.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly, That every <hi>Gentleman</hi> who will go <hi>for Ireland,</hi> on theſe Conditions, ſhall <hi>out of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>his ſhare of the</hi> 15000 <hi>l. buy</hi> a good Muſquet or Caſe of Piſtols, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>and every Relation or Servant that he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries over with him able to bear Arms;</hi> without the producing of which Arms in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the making Oath that he himſelf bought the ſame in <hi>England,</hi> he ſhall have no <hi>title</hi> to any of the ſaid 45000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect-money may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that one 3d part for the Relief of <hi>Women only,</hi> and the other two 3ds ſent for <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Encouragement of Tenants and Labourers to go over, to plow and ſow for the Nobility and Gentry, or for themſelves; and that theſe alſo, when they have entred their names to the Biſhops, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commiſſioners of the Collect-money, that they will go, they ſhall receive, if they go from <hi>London,</hi> 20 ſhill. or if near the Sea, 10 ſhill. <hi>apiece</hi> to bear their Charges, and a good Muſquet, or Caſe of Piſtols, <hi>at Cheſter,</hi> (which the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall provide, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>pay for out of their Stock) and the reſt of the Money they ſhall have divided among them at their arrival in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that all ſuch as will not go, ſhall find no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief here.</p>
               <p>We know by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that there are in all about 10000 men that will go over; and by this means his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty will, as it were, ſend a Recruit to the Army of ſo many freſh <hi>Inniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi> Men, inſpired with rage for their Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; Men, who when they get into their Countrey, will not be driven out again. So that our Army need not be weakned by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gariſons into any Town, but may march on entire; and theſe men will keep the Towns and Countrey behind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="scheme">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>
               <head>The ſecond Scheme.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is humbly propoſed that the King would <hi>be pleaſed</hi> to cauſe it to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>be made known <hi>publickly,</hi> That all the Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who now are in <hi>England,</hi> and whoſe uſual abode has been in <hi>Ireland,</hi> do forthwith return to that <hi>half</hi> of that Kingdom which is under His Majeſty's Authority, <hi>under pain of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Diſpleaſure,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch whom His Majeſty ſhall particularly order to ſtay here for His Service; and for their encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo to do, it is humbly propoſed,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, That His Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed to give to His <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Subjects of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the Sum of 60000 <hi>l. Ster.</hi> and that it be put into the Hands of two ſubſtantial wealthy Gentlemen of that kingdom, of known Integrity, and that are not Dealers in Money, who may be Treaſurers of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>the ſame, they giving ſufficient and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Security for the payment of <hi>the ſame</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is hereafter lay'd down, and that without any Fees, or other Charges to be pay'd by the perſons who are to receive it.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>
               <p n="3">3dly, <hi>That the King would declare that no Perſon of</hi> Ireland <hi>ſhould have Benefit of the ſaid Money, but ſuch as will go over to that Part of the Kingdom which is already Conquered, and there Sow Summer-Corn on their Eſtates (if they be of that Countrey) or on ſuch Eſtates of the</hi> Iriſh <hi>as the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners (for that purpoſe to be appointed) ſhall Aſſign to them, if their own Eſtates be in the Enemies Poſſeſſion; Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows only excepted, who ſhall yet have but a fourth part, or what their ſhare would have amounted to out of</hi> 15000 <hi>l.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4thly, That His Majeſty would be pleaſed to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a number of Comiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Nobility and Gentry of the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who know all the Eſtates of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that lie among theirs; and that theſe Commiſſioners may have authority to ſet out and aſſign the Eſtates of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> as are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>willing to ſow Summer-Corn thereon, for the next year only; and that every perſon whoſe ſhare of the ſaid Money ſhall amount to above 20 <hi>l.</hi> ſhall give Bonds to the ſaid Treaſurers in the King's Name, to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of what he receives, That for every 10 <hi>l.</hi> which he ſhall receive, he will ſow three Acres of Oats, Barley, or Peaſe. Upon his giving of theſe Bonds, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall give him an Order to receive his ſhare of Money from the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, For the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of all ſuch to go over, whoſe Eſtates are in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies poſſeſſion, <hi>it may be declared, that they ſhall have</hi> 5 <hi>parts to the others three; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that the ſhares of all ſuch as will not go over (except as before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) ſhall be divided among them,</hi> becauſe of the neceſſity they will lie under of <hi>building for themſelves ſome conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Dwelling upon Land which is not their own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6thly, That the Treaſurers, or one of them, <hi>ſhall ride about, and ſee</hi> that every perſon do ſow as much Corn as by Bond he was obliged to do; and that the ſame be not negligently thrown into the ground, only to eſcape
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>the Penalty of the Bond; therefore that at Harveſt-time the ſaid Treaſurers ſhall ride about <hi>again</hi> to ſee the ſame reaped; and that the Bonds ſhall be in force againſt all thoſe who have not their ſhare of Corn to reap, altho they did before anſwer the Obligation of their Bond, by Sowing. By this means, His Majeſty's fatherly Care of His People will moſt evidently appear, in contriving that his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects there ſhall have <hi>near</hi> 10000 Acres of Corn the next year; whereas without this, <hi>probably</hi> there will not be an handful in the whole Kingdom, and thouſands muſt die for want of Bread.</p>
               <p n="7">7thly, That every <hi>Gentleman</hi> who will go on theſe Conditions, <hi>ſhall receive from the ſaid Treaſurers</hi> 20 <hi>ſhiil. a man (being part of the ſaid</hi> 66000 <hi>li.</hi>) to buy <hi>him</hi> a good Muſquet, or Caſe of Piſtols, <hi>and alſo ſhall have a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable proportion to bear his Charges over,</hi> viz. <hi>all they whoſe ſhares do come to</hi> 50 <hi>l. or under, ſhall have out of their ſhare</hi> 40 <hi>s. a head (not reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Servants) and all whoſe charges exceed that, ſhall have</hi> 3 <hi>l. a head, as aforeſaid; this, if they go from</hi> London, <hi>and but</hi> 20 <hi>s. a head, if they be near the Sea: We know by computation that there are about</hi> 10000 <hi>that will go over; and by this means his Majeſty will, as it were, ſend a Recruit of ſo many to the Army, which will be as ſo many freſh</hi> Inniskilling Men, inſpired with Rage for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>their Loſſes; Men, who, when they get into their Country, will not be driven out again; ſo that our Army need not be weakned by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gariſons into any Town, but may march on entire; and theſe Men will keep the Towns and Country behind them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the Collect-Money may be divided, and one third kept here for the relief of <hi>Women only,</hi> and the two other thirds ſent for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for the encouragement of Tenants and Labourers to go over, to Plough and Sow for the Nobility and Gentry, or Themſelves; and that theſe <hi>Men</hi> alſo, when they have entred their names to the Biſhops, and other Commiſſioners of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect-Money, that they will go, they ſhall receive, if they go from <hi>London,</hi> 20 <hi>s.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece; or if <hi>at</hi> the Sea, or near, 10 <hi>s.</hi> to bear their Charges, and a good Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, or Caſe of Piſtols, (which the Commiſſioners ſhall provide, and pay for out of their Stock), and thereſt of the Money they ſhall divide amongſt them at their arrival in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that all ſuch as will not go, ſhall find no more Relief here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="scheme">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50986:5"/>
               <head>The Scheme as it is Printed.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is humbly propoſed that the King would cauſe it to be made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>known <hi>to be His plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> That all the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who now are in <hi>England,</hi> and whoſe uſual abode has been in <hi>Ireland,</hi> do forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to that part of that kingdom which is under His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Authority, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch whom His Majeſty ſhall particularly order to ſtay here for His Service; and that for their encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement ſo to do, it is humbly propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, That His Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed to give to <hi>all</hi> His <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects of <hi>Ireland, whoſe Eſtates have been returned into the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and by them have been Rated, the ſum of</hi> 15000 <hi>l. to be there diſtributed to ſuch of them as will go over to that part of the Kingdom which is already Conquered,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50986:6"/>and there Sow Summer-Corn,</hi> and that the ſaid 45000 <hi>l.</hi> be put into the Hands of two ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, wealthy Gentlemen of that Kingdom, Men of <hi>clear Eſtates, without any Incumbrance or Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements,</hi> of known In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and that are not Dealers in Money, who may be Treaſurers of the ſame, they giving ſufficient and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Security for the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>the ſaid</hi> 45000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is hereafter lay'd down, and that without any Fees or other Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be pay'd by the Perſons who are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; <hi>and that every Perſon, whoſe ſhare of the ſaid</hi> 45000 <hi>l. ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to</hi> 20 <hi>l. or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſhall give Bond to the ſaid Treaſurers in the King's name, to the value of what he receives, that for every</hi> 10 <hi>l. that he ſhall receive, he will Sow, if he be upon his own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, four Acres of</hi> Oats, Barley, <hi>or</hi> Peaſe, <hi>upon his giving of which Bonds, he ſhall receive his ſhare of Money from the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>
               <p n="3">3dly, For the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of all ſuch to go over, whoſe Eſtates are yet <hi>uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, it is propoſed,</hi> That they <hi>ſhall</hi> be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to Sow but Two Acres of Corn for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ten pounds that they ſhall receive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the neceſſity that they will lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>being at ſome Expence upon Land which is not their own, and of paying ſome ſmall Rent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4thly, That the ſaid Treaſurers, or one of them, ſhall <hi>take care</hi> that every perſon do ſow as much Corn as by Bond he was obliged to do, and that the ſame be not negligently thrown upon the ground, only to eſcape the Penalty of the Bond. And therefore that at Harveſt-time the ſaid Treaſurers, or one of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50986:7"/>them, ſhall ride about to ſee the ſame <hi>before it be</hi> reap'd; and that the Bonds ſhall be in force againſt all thoſe who have not their ſhare of Corn to reap <hi>(that is, if the ſame have happened through any neglect of theirs),</hi> altho they did before anſwer the Obligation of their Bond, by Sowing. By this means, His Majeſty's fatherly Care of His People will moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently appear, in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that His Subjects there ſhall have <hi>at leaſt</hi> 10000. Acres of Corn the next year; whereas without this, <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly</hi> there will not be an handful in the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and thouſands muſt die for want of Bread.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That every <hi>Perſon</hi> who will go for <hi>Ireland</hi> on theſe Conditions, ſhall out of his firſt ſhare <hi>of Money,</hi> buy for himſelf, and <hi>every Relation and Servant that he carries with him (who are able to bear Arms)</hi> a good Muſquet, or Caſe of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols <hi>for the Defence of his Family;</hi> without the producing of which Arms in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the making Oath that he himſelf bought the ſame in <hi>England,</hi> he ſhall have no right to receive any of the ſaid 45000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect-money may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that one 3d part of it may be kept here of it may be kept here for the Relief of <hi>Widows and Orphans only;</hi> and the other two thirds ſent for <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the encouragement of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Labourers to go over to plow and ſow for the Nobility and Gentry, or themſelves; and that theſe alſo, when they have entred their names to the Bps, and other Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Collect-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that they will go, they ſhall receive, if they go from <hi>London,</hi> 20 <hi>s.</hi> apiece; or if from the <hi>Sea-ſide, or near it,</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> apiece to bear their Charges, and a good Muſquet, or Caſe of Piſtols, at <hi>Cheſter and Briſtol,</hi> which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall provide and pay for out of their Stock, and the leſt of the Money they ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50986:8"/>have divided among them at their arrival in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that all ſuch of them as will not go over, ſhall find no Relief here.</p>
               <p>We already know by computation, that there are about 10000 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that will go over; and by this means His Majeſty will, as it were, ſend a Recruit to the Army <hi>(though it is not at all hereby intended that they ſhall be put into it)</hi> which will be as ſo many freſh <hi>Inniskilling Men,</hi> inſpired with Rage for their Loſſes; Men, who, when they get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ther Country, will not be driven out again. So that our Army need not be weakned by putting Gariſons into any Towns, but may march on entire; and theſe will keep the Towns and Country behind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And now have not <hi>the Anſwerers of this Propoſal</hi> much Reaſon to cry out, <hi>that this is not the ſame with that which lay before them?</hi> that it differs in Alterations (but <hi>no Amendments) more of Matter, than Phraſe.</hi> And whereas he alledgeth, that <hi>this might have lain before them, and ſaved a great deal of needleſs Trouble, but they poſitively refuſed it.</hi> I appeal to his own Conſcience and Ingenuity (if his Ambition to be a Politician have not ſtifled the Sentiments of a Gentleman) whether thoſe Perſons (who ſate in the Committee to conſider of the Papers communicated to them by the Orders of the Lords of the Council) did not offer, and conſent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50986:9"/>with the Projector, that he might retract one of thoſe Papers, if he would own, and ſubſcribe the other; which he reſuſing to do, and withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Huff, they proceeded to what lay before them. But if any of them dealt ſo uncivilly with that <hi>poor Paper,</hi> as to <hi>doom it to light a Pipe of Tobacco,</hi> or <hi>cendemn it to a</hi> worſe Imployment, I cannot apprehend how this ſhould argue any want of <hi>Loyalty, and Reſpect to His Majeſty;</hi> I rather think it a high Preſumption in the Vindicator, to intereſs His Majeſty in the ſoſtering of his Abortive Conceptions. But as I cannot believe, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that His Majeſty would ſpend <hi>ten Days in the Peruſal of it</hi> (whoſe piercing Judgment would diſcover the Emptineſs of thoſe Papers in the ſpace of ten Minutes) ſo I account it no wonder, that <hi>it lay near three Weeks before the Lords of the Privy Council;</hi> where, I perſuade my ſelf, it might have lain till Doomſday in the Afternoon, if the fond Father had not cry'd to have his Child reſtor'd to him. And doubtleſs they thought it fitter for the Conſideration of a more Inferior Aſſembly, to whom they remitted it; it being below their Wiſdom, and high Imployment, to throw away their Time on ſuch Paltry Buſineſs: And happy had it been for this Young Stateſman, if it had pleas'd them to commit thoſe crude No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Bundle of Waſt Papers; then the unhappy Author had not publiſh'd ſo ungrateful a <hi>Propoſal,</hi> nor exaſperated the whole Body of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants by ſo unhandſome a <hi>Vindication.</hi> And tho he very rudely and unkindly taunts the Gentleman who expreſſed a diſlike of his new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled Whimſies; yet <hi>when Judges, Attorny, and Sollicitor Generals Places come to be diſpoſed of in</hi> Ireland, I dare ſay, there will be found (even among thoſe of that Committee) men very competently qualified for ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and truly worthy to ſerve His Majeſty in the greateſt Truſt.</p>
               <p>His Second Argument is a meer wheedle, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſting in <hi>the Approbation of a great many of the Gentry of our own Country:</hi> and with what a convincing Inſtance does he prove this? why it is <hi>the Senſe</hi> of his <hi>moſt humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> R. T. Truly, if he do not produce Credentials, that this Single-ſoul'd Gentleman, <hi>R. T.</hi> was imploy'd to repreſent the Senſe of a great many more; I muſt conclude that his right Name is <hi>Legion,</hi> that he carries a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in his Guts. But if the <hi>Vindicator</hi> writ to ſome Perſons, on whom he has an Influence, in <hi>Leverpool,</hi> and dictated, and beſpoke their Anſwer (which is more than whiſper'd among us) it was an eaſie matter for him to tranſcribe it for the Preſs. And becauſe <hi>the Gentlemen in</hi> Cheſter ſeem'd to be <hi>prejudiced by miſ-repreſentations of it from</hi> London, the Craſty Proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor writ an inſulting Letter to <hi>Cheſter,</hi> that the Gentlemen, who anſwered his <hi>Propoſal,</hi> were aſhamed of it, and rebuked for it; which, how falſe ſoever, yet he by often repetition of that Fiction, at laſt imagin'd it to be real, and true. But to confront <hi>R. T.</hi> and thoſe at <hi>Leverpool,</hi> I will ſet up <hi>T. T.</hi> and produce a Letter from him, in which may be ſeen <hi>the Senſe of the Gentlemen in</hi> Cheſter.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50986:9"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p rend="margSglQuotes">WE had hopes of having the 15000 <hi>l.</hi> ſpeedily, but I fear it may be delayed, if not quite loſt, by ſome of our own Peoples fooliſh doings: By this laſt we had an Account of Sir <hi>R. B</hi>'s Project, to cauſe Plowing and Sowing Oats in the <hi>North;</hi> he wrote a Letter to Captain <hi>Foſter,</hi> to prevail with us here, to Subſcribe our Conſent to his Project, but at the ſame time never ſent us the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the thing, ſo that he muſt either take us for Fools, or that we have a mighty implicite Faith and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on his Parts and Intereſt; all that he mentioned in his Letter was, that 45000 Pound ſhould be advanced and paid to the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> in this Kingdom, who ſhould return to the <hi>North,</hi> and fall to Plowing and Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oats, for which they ſhould have 5 Pound <hi>per</hi> Acre, which (if his Propoſals to the Parliament conſiſt of no other Particulars) is one of the wildeſt and moſt unlikely Projects, to take effect, that ever I heard of. I doubt not but every body would be glad that good ſtore of Corn were ſowed in the <hi>North</hi> againſt the next Seaſon, and that there were ſome probable Meaſures taken to incourage it, but no body can imagine that the King or Parliament (who I believe have occaſions enough for all the Money they can raiſe) ſhould advance 45000 Pound, to ſow Nine thouſand Acres of Land, which may be bought at Harveſt time for 18000 Pound, for Oats was never yet worth at moſt 40 Shillings <hi>per</hi> Acre; nay and the Party that ſowes the Land to have the Corn afterwards. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve if the King would for encouragement beſtow 4 <hi>s. per</hi> Acre on the Weilder, which would buy Seed or pay the Rent, 'twould be much cheaper to the King, than to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance 45000 Pound, and it would certainly encourage the People of the <hi>North</hi> to ſow enough for the Army next Summer; or if ſome abatement were made the Country in Exciſe and Chimny Money, proportionable to what they ſhould Plow, perhaps it might encourage them to do ſomething; for my ſhare I pretend not to projecting, but if this of Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> be, (as we are informed by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50986:10"/>other Letters it is) that all who ſhall receive any of the 15000 Pound, muſt be obliged to go into the <hi>North</hi> to ſow Oats, I fancy he deſigns to hinder the Payment of it, for on thoſe Terms few certainly will take any of it; for does the Knight think that the Gentlemen of the Quill, and Tradeſmen, and others, who never underſtood any thing of the Plow, (and who if they ſhould undertake it would do more hurt than good at it) ſhould go into the <hi>North</hi> and turn Plowmen, without any proſpect of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or other Materials for plowing, or of Houſes to lye in? For I believe thoſe are ſcarce enough to quarter the Army: Or does he intend to Tranſport the other three Provinces into <hi>Ulſter?</hi> I believe his Worſhip will preſerve his own Perſon in <hi>England,</hi> and cares not what becomes of a great many better; if it be left to every ones Choice (by his Project) whether they will go on thoſe Terms of 5 <hi>l. per</hi> Acre, or ſtay, I doubt not but the Gentlemen of the <hi>North</hi> themſelves will (if they be ſure of the Money) earn it all; or if Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> has a mind that ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of other Provinces ſhould mix with the Northern Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this Affair; there is Sir <hi>F. B.</hi> who we hear is a joint Projector with Sir <hi>R. B.</hi> and others, who I could name at <hi>London,</hi> who I believe with little intreaty will take all the Money on any Terms they will part with it; and ſo I have done with Sir <hi>R. B</hi>'s Project, which I would not have medled with, had I any thing elſe to do.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>T. T.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Perhaps in the Third place <hi>ſome of thoſe who were there</hi> (and the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> conſiſted of there times <hi>Fifty</hi>) did <hi>miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it,</hi> that is to ſay did approve it: (the Number of whom will hardly reach to make a <hi>Mournival</hi>) perhaps ſome of his few Accomplices may have ſubſcribed a Paper, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing a ſenſe conſonant to his Propoſal; yet I am apt to ſuſpect this Aſſertion, ſince the <hi>Vindicator</hi> (who has pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſo readily his <hi>Propoſal, and the Leverpool-Letter</hi>) has forborn to ſtuff this Subſcription into his Farce. But be as it will, it is undeniably certain, that <hi>the Senſe of the Gentry at their meeting ran generally againſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50986:10"/>
               <p>As for what he ſays of the <hi>Committee,</hi> conſiſting <hi>of three out of a Province;</hi> if that was not a fair way, I would deſire to know in what manner can he Project that a <hi>Committee</hi> ſhould be choſen? it muſt be a ſelect Number, elſe it is no Election: Buſineſs muſt be appointed to them, elſe they are no Committee; it muſt conſiſt of ſuch as are preſent, and muſt be named by them who are preſent; and I am ſure that in the great and ſolemn Aſſembly of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Members <hi>name</hi> one another, and ſo they become a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee. But let him ſay what he pleaſes, I very well remember that the Eſtabliſhing of that Committee was done withal Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without Diſpute or Conteſt, until two (either nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the Projector, or ſuſpected to be in Conſpiracy with him) were publickly, and with ſome Reſentment, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
               <p>He takes the liberty to ſay, that he <hi>ſaw at their Table ſome Gentlemen of</hi> Munſter, <hi>whoſe Eſtates ſingly are by all their Neighbours owned to be more than the Eſtates in</hi> Ireland <hi>of the three Perſons, who now ſtand for that Province in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee.</hi> This is conſidently ſpoken, and very idly; for it is notorious to the Neighbours in <hi>Munſter,</hi> that if the Eſtates of thoſe Perſons, who ſtood for the Provincce of <hi>Munſter</hi> in that Committee, were diſcovered and laid in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, they would poiſe with any as many Gentlemen of <hi>Munster</hi> at that Table; and would certainly outweigh thoſe two, who ſtickled at that time for the Place, though the Projectors Eſtate were caſt in with them to help the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe it true, <hi>that ſeven or eight of thoſe twelve Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens are in ſuch good Circumſtances here, that they would not return, if the whole Kingdom were reduced,</hi> does that render them unqualified to be of the <hi>Committee?</hi> or if <hi>others fetcht over thouſands in Caſh;</hi> and will generouſly <hi>releaſe their claim to any ſhare of the Fifteen thouſand Pounds;</hi> or are <hi>called to the Bar,</hi> and <hi>in</hi> ſome ſmall <hi>Practice here;</hi> are not they the more fit, and more impartial Arbiters of what is moſt conducing to the Benefit of <hi>Ireland?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The remainder of the Paragraph is in coherent, and not well tacked to the reſt, and by the forced Inference, or Application, <hi>(that ſome Gentlemen, who had good Eſtates, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50986:11"/>great Stocks, are become diſtracted by exceſſive wants.</hi> I might have ſuſpected that the Author had pointed at himſelf, had he not mentioned <hi>the putting of Daughters, young Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men well educated, to Service:</hi> for I think the Projectors Children are not yet grown up to that Maturity. And I retort his own Words. <hi>What barbarous Cruelty is it to hinder Men from getting Relief (how dear ſoever they pay for it) who otherwiſe may be forced to ſtarve, or perhaps to put an end to their miſerable Days with their own Hands?</hi> But let God and the World judg, who it is that has maliciouſly, or ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt contributed to ſuch unfortunate Poſſibilities.</p>
               <p>Theſe Men are not <hi>unwilling to go themſelves,</hi> but probab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Reaſons may be ſuch, as will demonſtrate it <hi>un-pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable for others to go,</hi> upon ſuch deluſive Terms as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector has contrived. Therefore, to follow his Method, I will impart to the Reader the very <hi>Anſwer</hi> drawn up by the <hi>Committee,</hi> and preſented to the Lords of the Council.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Anſwer of ſuch of the Nobility, Gentry, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as are now in and about the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to a Project contain'd in Three Papers; which were by the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lords of the Committee of Council for the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> deliver'd to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> to be communicated to them.</head>
               <p>WE having ſeen and duly conſider'd the aforeſaid Papers, do humbly offer</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That many of the Allegations and Suggeſtions in the ſaid Papers contained, and on which the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is founded, are notoriouſly falſe, or very fallacious; as for Example.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Suggeſtion that half, or near half of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland</hi> is reduced, is not true, for really one fourth part of the Kingdom is not in his Majeſties Poſſeſſion; and even in the center of that part, the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as yet, keep the important Fort of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> to the great Annoyance, if not the total hindrance of Tillage in the Neighbourhood of that Garriſon.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50986:11"/>
               <p n="2">2. The Allegation, that the Proteſtants of that reduc'd part are moſt of them in <hi>England</hi> is as untrue, it being certain that not a twentieth, and we believe not the fortieth part of them are now in this Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Aſſertion, that the conſequence of the ſtay of the Iriſh Proteſtants here muſt be a Famine there, is a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and the quite contrary is more likely; for if they were there, they and their Families would eat more than they could ſow, or the Projector propoſes they ſhould ſow, and conſequently would haſten and encreaſe the Famine rather than prevent it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Suggeſtion, that too much of the Charity-money is expended to feed the luxury and idleneſs of ſome that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it is very ſcandalous and no leſs falſe; ſince the ſmall ſum given to any one perſon is too little to adminiſter to his wants, much leſs his luxury; and it is manifeſt by the Book and reports of the Commiſſioners, that the Charity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money is diſtributed with as much care and caution as is poſſible, and very little of it is given to any of the Gentry, and that ſparingly to ſuch as greatly need it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Inſinuation, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> who now fly before our Army, would gladly return and ſettle again under their old Maſters, is offer'd at adventure, and it is much more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the influence their Clergy have over them, and the Wrongs they have already done to their old Maſters and Neighbours would hinder them from returning. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Country, to which thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> are now fled, is far better and more Fertile than the reduc'd parts are, and ſo they are invited back to their loſs; but if they had any ſuch intention to return, yet this Argument is fallacious as to all the reſt of the Nobility and Gentry that have no Eſtates nor Tenants in <hi>Ulſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The main Suppoſition of all (<hi>viz.</hi> That there is want of Men in <hi>Ulster</hi> to till the Land) is not true; for there is not ſuch want of Men there; but that which is really wanting in order to Tillage, is Seed, Corn, Cattle for the Plough, and other Neceſſaries.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Suggeſtion, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are fearful to return, is very injurious and falſe; for it is manifeſt that the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> deſire nothing more than an opportunity to ſerve his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50986:12"/>Majeſty, the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt in the reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Kingdom, and have always declared their readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo to do, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe his Majeſty to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them thereunto.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Aſſertion, that thoſe who will not go to <hi>Ulſter</hi> will be left without excuſe, is a great miſtake, for it is a a juſt excuſe for any Man not to engage in ſo unreaſonable a Project, when the Grounds of it are untrue, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of it impracticable.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Projector ſaith, that if the 60000 <hi>l.</hi> he not now ſent over, and the Proteſtants ſent away to ſow Corn there, a greater Sum than now pays the Army, will not ſuffice to buy Bread to keep the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> that are now in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> next Year. If that ſhould be true, yet the Projector has not by any Propoſal in theſe Papers offer'd any method to obviate it; for he propoſes only ſowing 10000 Acres, which will not ſerve thoſe that ſow them and their Families.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The Suggeſtion, that there are many forfeited Eſtates in <hi>Ulſter</hi> (which is another Pillar of this Project) is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly untrue; for there were fewer <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts reſtor'd to their Eſtates in this Province then in any other in that Kingdom: So that there are no other conſiderable Eſtates in that part of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> now in our Quarters, that belong'd to ſuch <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, except the Earl of <hi>Antrim</hi>'s, Lord <hi>Strabane</hi>'s and Sir <hi>Neal O Neale</hi>'s; and 'tis well known moſt part of thoſe Eſtates are in Poſſeſſion of Proteſtants by ſettlement in Jointures, Leaſes, Mortgages, or other Incumbrances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The propos'd Method is altogether impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to the Proclamation propos'd, it is without Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent or Law to oblige any perſon to improve and dwell upon another Mans Eſtate; and if it be anſwered, That the propos'd Encouragement will invite them, then there need no ſuch Proclamation; for Intereſt is attractive enough without other Obligations, but the quite contrary appears by the general diſlike of thoſe Propoſals.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Inconvenience, Charge and Trouble of ſo tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Journey at this time of the Year, and the hazard and trouble of paſſing the Seas, would be ſo inſupportable, that very few would be found to undertake it; but above all,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50986:12"/>there being no Houſes or Conveniences for the Reception and Entertainment of ſo many Families of the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, as the Projector propoſes, ſhould go to that reduced part, renders the whole Project unreaſonable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Either the number that will go will be very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, or their proportion of the Mony not ſufficient to bear the charge of the Voyage. The Propoſer writes of ten thouſand men that he has computed will go over, if ſo the 60000 <hi>l.</hi> will be but ſix pound apiece one with another; and when the price of a Muſquet, or a Caſe of Piſtols, and the Charge of the Journey and Voyage are deducted from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, there will not be enough left to ſupport them, and much leſs to build Houſes, buy Bedding (not to mention other Furniture) and to buy Seed-corn, Horſes, and all other Neceſſaries for the Plough.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It ſeems very improbable, as well as unreaſonable, that any perſon of the other Provinces ſhould be induc'd to go to <hi>Ulſter</hi> and build a Houſe, and give it up at a years end, and live miſerably in it the mean time.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is unlikely that two ſuch ſubſtantial wealthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of clear and unſetled Eſtates, of known In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and not Dealers in Mony (as the Propoſer deſcribes them) can be found, who will take upon them to be Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers of the 45000 <hi>l.</hi> upon the terms propoſed, or that can give ſufficient and undoubted Security for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That it would be great ſeverity, and no leſs diſſervice to his Majeſty, to force the Inhabitants of the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces ſo far from their Eſtates and Relations, ſince they are ſo forward to aſſiſt all ſuch Attempts and Impreſſions as His Majeſties Forces ſhall make in their reſpective Provinces, where they may be much more uſeful.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To ſend the Nobility and Gentry of a Kingdom to till the Land, and to build Houſes in a Country ſo impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd, in the Winter-time, when neither Timber, Brick, Mortar, or other Materials for Building can be had in that Country, nor Firing, nor Victuals to comfort and ſupport them till the Corn be reap'd; and to oblige all the ſeveral degrees of Men of that Kingdom to reap their Corn, and to lie under their Bonds, tho they have duly ſown their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, unleſs they do alſo reap it, would be an Injunction
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50986:13"/>far more rigorous than thoſe of the <hi>Egyptian</hi>-Task-maſters. And now having demonſtrated, as we preſume, That the aforeſaid Project, is founded upon many falſe Suppoſitions and is in it ſelf impracticable for the Reaſons aforeſaid, and many others, we humbly hope that the Project will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; in all things moſt humbly ſubmitting to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties great Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>And when he ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>That His Majeſty and his Privy-Council were well ſatisfied of the great Neceſſity and Benefit of the Propoſal, and therefore gave it into the Hands of ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to conſider,</hi> &amp;c. I take this to be arrogantly and preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly inſinuated, Why may it not as reaſonably be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that His Majeſty and His Privy-Council, to rid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Projectors Importunity, remitted it to ſome Perſons of our Country, who, they well foreſaw, would ſoon diſcover how impracticable and utterly vain the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal is, and ſo would damn it? and I am clearly of his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That <hi>it was not at all to have theſe Gentlemens approbation of it,</hi> for they in their Wiſdom knew it would never be approved by them.</p>
               <p>Moſt unkindly ſaid! to call the poor robbed Proteſtants <hi>a Rabble.</hi> It is not likely that the Rabble could tranſport themſelves and Families into <hi>England:</hi> and I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that thoſe honeſt People who compoſed that Croud (howſoever they might make no ſplendid Appearance here) made no contemptible Figure in their own Country. But to account <hi>Sollicitors, Attornies, Clerks,</hi> &amp;c. ſo, and to make them a parcel of <hi>the Rabble,</hi> is a moſt injudicious and ſcandalous Cenſure; ſince their way of Education at School, at the Inns of Court, and Practiſe in the Courts of Juſtice, may fairly abſolve them from the Ignominy of ſuch a Character: beſide that it is notorious, that ſome who appear'd there, and do paſs under the Denomination of <hi>Clerks,</hi> are able to vie with the Projector in <hi>Eſtates and Plantations.</hi> As peremptory is his Claim to nuzzle himſelf under the Kings Robes, and pretend, that an <hi>Affront offered to him, is the ſame as if done to his Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now behold a wonder! no ſooner did the mighty Man enter the Room, but the two inconſiderable Fellows of that Committee, who penned that ſcurrilous and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50986:13"/>Anſwer, were abſolutely confounded; and he that was reading it to the Aſſembly was ſtruck ſilent, by the Magick Power of his preſence: nay, they were ſo confounded with the ſenſe of their own <hi>Scurrility, and Reflections, that for ſhame, they could not read any more, till he was gone;</hi> and after he was gone <hi>(mark that)</hi> then <hi>the Author began to beg Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of the Projector.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the beſt of my remembrance, there was but one draught of an Anſwer laid before the Committee (though tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed twice, becauſe of ſome Blottings, and Interlineations) while moſt of them preſent had ſo deſpicable an Opinion of this Chymerical Project; that had it not been honored with a Paſtport from the Lords of the Committee, it had been anſwered only with Ha, Ha, He: in the mean Time <hi>if he be a ſtranger to the Contents of the Anſwer agreed on by the Committee,</hi> how comes the <hi>Vindicator</hi> to take Notice of it? and to anſwer the Paragraphs of it, <hi>page</hi> 11, &amp; 14. And where he ſuggeſteth, <hi>that the Gentleman at the Delivery of their Anſwer, received a ſevere Reproof to themſelves,</hi> it is wholly untrue in matter of Fact: the Anſwer was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in by the ſame perſon, to whom the Propoſal was given by the Lords of the Council, from whom there came no Reproof, nor the leaſt ſignification of any Diſlike.</p>
               <p>It is but the Projectors malicious Fancy, that the <hi>Northern Gentry will be ordered to go without mony,</hi> as it is wildly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, that <hi>ſome of them refuſed to go with mony.</hi> They have not deſerved ſo ill at His Majeſty's Hands, by quiting their Eſtates, and Habitations, out of pure Zeal to their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and untainted Loyalty to Him, rather than live under the Tyranny of their Oppreſſors, or voluntarily contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to promote the Intereſt of the implacable Enemies to King, and Country. But as none of them have reſiſted the Temptation of Mony to tranſport them; ſo none will demur upon the Kings Commands, if He think fit to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige them to return, though they ſhould beg by the way.</p>
               <p>And ſince he has ſo uncharitably pronounced, that <hi>their ſtaying here is unaccountable,</hi> it is well for them, that he has founded his Doom upon a falſe Bottom, <hi>That ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that Country of the beſt Quality have not loſt out of their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50986:14"/>Houſes, to the value of a Silver Spoon.</hi> If there be ſuch a Houſe, it muſt be ſome inchanted Caſtle; for had it been viſible either to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> it had not eſcaped a more detrimental Inquiſition, nor compounded for ſo little Damage with the Military Romagers. I know one Perſon of Quality <hi>(the Lord Viſcount Maſſareen)</hi> who, beſide rich and plentiful Furniture in his Houſe, and a mighty ſtock of Horſes, Mares, and Cattle upon his Demeſns, has loſt above Three thouſand pounds worth of Plate in his Houſe, and has not ſaved of it <hi>ſo much as a Silver Spoon.</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he means thoſe, whom before he hinted at, <hi>who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved their Goods and Effects long before this Revolution,</hi> and ſo were out of Danger of loſing <hi>out of their Houſes to the value of a Silver Spoon.</hi> Yet even they (though they may have <hi>ſaved ſome Mony, Plate, or Houſholdſtuff)</hi> are deprived of their Rents, and will be forced (if they have not begun already) to live upon the Stock, and convert their Goods into neceſſary Food.</p>
               <p>His Objections are but the Tranſcript of the Committees Anſwer ſet down before, and it were a needleſs Repetition to ſay them over again. I look upon them as unſhaken, notwithſtanding all his undermining, and bombarding. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I ſhall look over his <hi>Reply,</hi> and endeavour to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his new Batteries forceleſs, and ineffectual.</p>
               <p>Indeed if it were poſſible, or probable, <hi>that the Return of a few</hi> into a deſolate and ruined Country, would tend to the Preſervation of them that <hi>will ſtay here:</hi> then (to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to his Simile) it were good ſervice to throw ſome of the Paſſengers, and Goods over-bord, to lighten the Ship, and ſave the reſt: but if in a Tempeſt ſome of the Mariners ſhould leap into the Sea, to appeaſe the Storm, it would contribute little to the Succeſs of the Voyage.</p>
               <p>It is not impoſſible, but in the Counties of <hi>Down,</hi> and <hi>Antrim,</hi> and part of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> by the Care and Conduct of Duke <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and the circulation of Mony, Food, and Firing may be had: but in the other ſix Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries (where the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> muſt ramble, according to the Projectors Scheme) there were not Men to reap, no Horſes to gather in, their laſt Harveſt; and conſequently their <hi>Proviſion</hi> for the enſuing Year muſt need be skanty: and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50986:14"/>when by their Flight, and Deſertion of their Houſes, they had no opportunity to provide Turf, their ſtock of <hi>Firing</hi> cannot but be very ſlender.</p>
               <p>I will not take upon me to predict the Fate of <hi>ſuch as ſhould go there, and being there, ſhould be diſtreſſed for Proviſions.</hi> I do not doubt <hi>His Majesty's Care, and Tenderneſs:</hi> but at ſuch a Diſtance, many unforeſeen Accidents may intervene to fruſtrate, or prorogue His pious Intentions; while the poor Expectants muſt inevitably periſh.</p>
               <p>The inſtances of the <hi>Vandois,</hi> and of <hi>New-England</hi> are no way applicable to this Occaſion. The one are conducted with an Army, and Succeſs attends them; the other were ſafe in their own Dwellings, and were eaſily ſupply'd with Bread, which was their only want.</p>
               <p>But now without Queſtion the Man is in a Dream. He talks like a Hen wife, of Hens and Geeſe giving them Egs (as if he had lately come from Surveying <hi>Leaden-Hall,</hi> or the <hi>Stocks-Market)</hi> but will not know, nor underſtand, that in ſuch parts of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> where the Enemy have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaged, and even in many of thoſe where our Forces are quarter'd, there is not left a <hi>Hen</hi> to cackle, or a <hi>Cow</hi> to give them Milk.</p>
               <p>As we may with too much Sadneſs and Truth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict his Aſſertion, <hi>that all things are at preſent in great plenty in</hi> Ireland (ſince the contrary is too ſenſibly felt there, and the conſequence of it does aſcertain our Miſeries here) ſo I hope his preſages of <hi>Famine and Plague</hi> are not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Aſtrological Calculations:</hi> or if they be, may prove as erroneous as the Judgment of the <hi>Almanac Makers;</hi> and ſhall fall only on the Heads of them, who are Enemies to the King, and to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>Methinks I ſee Sir Poſitive ſtrut, and look big, when he aſſumes to himſelf the ſatisfaction, that <hi>the Government is of the ſame mind with him:</hi> and what a pertinent Reaſon he aſſigns for it? <hi>becauſe true Policy is the ſame in all wiſe States.</hi> This indeed is a delicate conceit, that when our King has thrown off all Dependency, and Correſpondence with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Projector will have him to take pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and imitate them in their Politicks. But ſince he is pleaſed to fix that glorious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50986:15"/>on his <hi>Propoſal,</hi> that it is <hi>agreeable to the ſentiments of the wiſe State of</hi> Rome (a Conſideration which would very much ingratiate him with King <hi>James,</hi> if he were but now at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and had ſucceeded Sir <hi>John Dary</hi>'s in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Principal Secretary of Scate</hi>) I am the leſs concern'd, that he has ſlander'd the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Gentlemen of <hi>Ireland</hi> with the ſcandalous Nick-name, of <hi>a Cabal of our Rabble,</hi> p. 14. by which he muſt need intend the Gentlemen, who took too much pains to anſwer ſuch an inſignificant piece of Foppery; becauſe he intimates, and ridicules them for <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up for</hi> Iriſh <hi>States men,</hi> which certainly none of the Rabble would aſpire to. I was either one of that Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or had ſome very good Friends in it, and therefore I have as much Reaſon to reſent a wound given to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, as the ill-natur'd Projector aſſumes to himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 20. in his Epilogue to that Libel, by which he has aſperſed the Honour of an honeſt and worthy Gentleman. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore henceforward I ſhall not treat him with that ſoftneſs, which I intended at the firſt.</p>
               <p>In the matter of his Politicks he might perhaps amuſe ſuch a poor <hi>Rabble</hi> as we are; but when he comes to talk like a Traveller, or an Intelligencer, he is lamentably out, and the moſt ignorant of us can diſprove him. For though there be no Army encamped near to <hi>Colrane, Belturbet, Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilling,</hi> or <hi>London-derry;</hi> yet in each of them there are ſo many Men in Garriſon, that together with the Inhabitants of thoſe reſpective places, there is no room to be had for ſtangers. But why will he ſhoot thus at random? With what confidence can he aver, that <hi>there are not in</hi> Derry <hi>twenty Houſes uninhabitable?</hi> When if he had inquired of twenty Perſons now reſident in <hi>London</hi> (who endured all the Miſeries of the Siege, and were Spectators of the Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that place) they would have aſſured him, as they have done me, that there are not in that City ten Houſes, which may be inhabited with ſafety, and convenience. And if there be <hi>ſix hundred Soldiers there,</hi> as he ſeems to ſuggeſt, for my part I ſtand in admiration how they are accommodated with Quarters: for in the time of Peace, when the City was very populous, and full of Trade, when there were more Houſes in the Suburbs, than within the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50986:15"/>Walls, there were ſeven Companies quarter'd there (which hardly would make up four hundred men) the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants grumbled, and complained grievouſly of it. This I do aver upon my own certain knowledg</p>
               <p>What an idle, and moſt improbable Whimſey has he found, as an Expedient to ſupply the Proteſtants with Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the Plough? That becauſe the <hi>Iriſh ran away in ſuch haſte at the landing of our Army, that they left their Corn ripe in the Field,</hi> it is as likely that they <hi>left their Plough-Garrons behind them:</hi> If they did ſo, is it not more likely that they have been taken up by our Army, who ſtood in ſuch need of <hi>Baggage-horſes?</hi> And can he imagine, that the Souldiers will part with them for the buſineſs of the Plough? Methinks this ſubtil Contriver (who has invented a new Imployment of Itenerant Superviſors to ſee the Corn ſowed and reaped) ſhould have propounded the ſending over two or three <hi>Muleteers, or Commiſſary Generals,</hi> to gather up the wandring Garrons of the Country, and to ſecure them in ſome Pin-fold, till they might coveniently be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted among the Gentlemen deſigned by him to till the ground at next Seed-time.</p>
               <p>What a lame incongruous Reaſon is this? <hi>Becauſe we ſhall find black Cattle enough in</hi> England, <hi>to carry back; therefore we may be ſupply'd with Horſes from</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Wales. This is ſo ridiculous, that it would diſparage a Mans Reaſon to go about to confute it.</p>
               <p>As little Ingenuity does he diſcover in his Anſwer to the next Objection. Becauſe we are <hi>Sojourners, and Lodgers in</hi> England, <hi>and pay dear for the uſe of Houſhold-goods, Beds,</hi> &amp;c. therefore we may ſojourn more cheaply in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where neither Houſhold-goods, nor Beds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to be had for Mony. How ſcanty is the Intelligence brought to this ſmall Politician? or how wilfully is he prejudicated in his Opinion? Tho in the Counties of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Antrim,</hi> many of the <hi>Inhabitants are returned to their Houſes,</hi> very ill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Houſhold ſtuff; yet in the other ſix Northern-Counties (<hi>eſpecially London derry, Tyrone,</hi> and <hi>Dongal</hi>) they are ſo far from having Beds to lie on, that for the moſt part they have not a place to lay a Bed in; the Gentlemens Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Market-Towns and Villages being utterly burnt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50986:16"/>And I am very confident, that of <hi>the many a Score of Ship-loads of Bedding, and other Houſhold-stuff brought into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, there will be but a ſmall ſhare left to be carry'd back again, ſince the Owners have been conſtrained by their Neceſſities to convert them into Mony for their daily Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. <hi>He that conſults</hi> (as he ſays) <hi>Briſtol, North-Wales, Cheſter, Leverpool,</hi> and <hi>Cumberland, will find this to be true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what! would he have us to go into a <hi>deſolate Country,</hi> only <hi>becauſe it is deſolate?</hi> And ſuppoſe the Gentlemen would condeſcend to become Holders and Drivers of the Plough, yet what ſhall they do with their Wives and Children? Where ſhall they ſtow them? And tho the Country be not poſſeſſed by the Enemy, yet the Garriſon of <hi>Charlemont,</hi> lying in the Center of <hi>Ulſter,</hi> may poſſibly make ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions as will mightily diſ-array the young Plough-men. But I perceive little <hi>Nehemiah</hi> would have us carry a <hi>Sword</hi> in one hand, and a <hi>Goad</hi> in the other.</p>
               <p>And where he inſinutes an Inclination in us to <hi>beggar one another by Indictments for Treſpaſſes, which has more of the Lawyer in it than the Christian</hi> (as if Chriſtian and Lawyer were in the Predicament of Oppoſites) I may well ſay, That his Suppoſition hath more of the Viper in it than the Lamb. And I wiſh alſo, that his ſnarling and cavilling do not <hi>give the People of</hi> England <hi>occaſion to think us litigious, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable People;</hi> or at leaſt very tame and ſupine to ſuffer one man with Impunity to abuſe a whole Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Silveſter Brown,</hi> who propos'd to the Council in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſettle Stages, and a Poſt-road between <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Holyhead,</hi> under the Sea; or he that would have O <hi>Braſile</hi> (being a floting Iſland) clapt in, like a Guſſet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that ſo they might become one intire Iſland, did not offer at a more impracticable Project, than this of <hi>Treaſurers, Superviſors, Riders, Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waiters,</hi> and <hi>Corn-Guarders.</hi> And tho perhaps he may have an Eye to <hi>two publick-ſpirited Men, duly qualify'd,</hi> who would poſtpone their private Advantage, and undertake this Labour for the <hi>publick Good;</hi> yet I remain in doubt, that even thoſe will hardly be perſwaded to practiſe ſo great Self-denial, as to undergo ſo much Hazard and Toil, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Proſpect of a Reward.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50986:16"/>
               <p>Truly he has placed a very obliging Complement on <hi>the Nobles of our Land,</hi> when he ſays, <hi>I bear as great a Reſpect to our Nobles, as the Anſwerers:</hi> And what Reſpect he bears to the Anſwerers (among whom alſo there were ſome of the Nobles preſent, and ſeveral were conſenting) may be judged by his former Civility, when he ſtyles them <hi>a Cabal of our Rabble,</hi> p. 14. <hi>who ſet up for Iriſh Stateſmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The noiſe he maketh about <hi>Proclamations and Precedents,</hi> is already ſtill'd by the Anſwer of the Committee. And who could have ſuſpected that a Proteſtant of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould have darted ſuce virulent Invectives againſt his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Neighbours? reproaching them with a fatal Lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>to ſtand looking at their Country, and not return, tho periſhing here with want;</hi> aggravating their Reſtineſs by a Compariſon with the <hi>French Refugees,</hi> and taxing the <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our King, in troubling himſelf to conquer a Country for a People who will not return and plant in it when it is conquer'd:</hi> which diſcovers his Judgment to be as ſhallow, as his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is canker'd. Neither is he leſs miſtaken in his <hi>Choro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy,</hi> when he ſuppoſeth the Security of <hi>London-derry,</hi> or <hi>Eniskill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng</hi> (the firſt of which is ſixty Miles diſtant, and the other above thirty) though the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are are <hi>Sligo,</hi> but makes no mention of <hi>Charlemont</hi> which may infeſt them in a days march. But what if <hi>London derry,</hi> and <hi>Eniskilling,</hi> and other Towns were out of danger? what if the new Planters could all be crouded into the Towns? where ſhall the Plough go? the Corn muſt be ſowed in the circumja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Counties, and who will cover and protect them when they are following their Labour? But the Gentleman has read <hi>Heylins Coſmography,</hi> and can tell to an Inch how far it is between the <hi>Country of</hi> Vandols <hi>and</hi> Turin; and how little a diſtance there is between <hi>Hunningen</hi> and <hi>Baſi.</hi> But to what purpoſe is this Hiſtorical Vaunt? where lyes the Elixir of the Application? If the <hi>Vandols</hi> had been up in Arms, and ravaged the Country to the Walls of <hi>Turin,</hi> it is very probable the <hi>Duke of Savoy</hi> would not have left <hi>Paris,</hi> and go keep his Court there: And if the People of <hi>Baſil</hi> had been driven out of the City, and ſhelter'd in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> I am ap to believe they would not have run in great haſt, much leſs would the <hi>States of Holland</hi> have by <hi>Proclamation</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50986:17"/>obliged them to return <hi>within Cannon ſhot</hi> of their Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Enemies.</p>
               <p>And now he gives you a Taſt of his Craft: So cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did he contrive to avoid the menace of the Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by <hi>a tacit Proviſo, that he is among thoſe, whoſe uſual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode has not been in</hi> Ireland: And indeed I ſuſpect a further reach in this State-Ingeneer; for that <hi>being ameng the firſt that ſhall go over to ſow Corn,</hi> and believing (as he hath before ſurmiſed) that the <hi>People will not return and Plant,</hi> when the Country is conquer'd; it is demonſtrable, that <hi>if His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will ſend over Money,</hi> and appoint his two Publick ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Friends to be Treaſurers, they will ſoon agree upon the Partition. In the mean time he need not take the pains to <hi>go out at the gate,</hi> when he may ſafely creep out at a <hi>Loop Hole;</hi> and if he can do His Majeſty more Service <hi>by ſowing Corn,</hi> than <hi>by staying here,</hi> it is Talent beyond what I ever heard that accompliſhed Gentleman pretend to. It is a Noble Art to be a good Seeds man; and I wonder he has not put in for a <hi>Monoply,</hi> or a Patent for fourteen years, to be the <hi>Sower-General.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems to be the deſign of the <hi>Vindicator,</hi> not ſo much to juſtifie the <hi>Propoſal</hi> (though at all times he diſcovers a Self-conceited fondneſs of it) as to aſperſe and villifie the Gentlemen of <hi>Ireland</hi> now reſident in <hi>London,</hi> repreſenting them as an inconſiderable Number; noting them rather as a Club, <hi>who get together upon every Occaſion;</hi> girding them with a ſecret Ambition of <hi>ſtaying for Imployments, or to be made Privy-Counſellors;</hi> and upbraiding them with an unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly Preſumption, <hi>in pretending to anſwer for a whole Nation, without conſulting,</hi> &amp;c. To this (though it may deſerve a Return of another Nature) I ſhall only anſwer by direct Contradiction: for neither is it true, <hi>that forty or fifty Men upon every occaſion,</hi> or that upon <hi>ſome Occaſions</hi> there met leſs than <hi>Three hunder'd;</hi> whoſe Reſolutions were conſented to by Five thouſand Perſons reſident in <hi>London,</hi> more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for Number and Quality, than thoſe in <hi>Briſtol, Cheſter, and Leverpool;</hi> neither has any thing been acted in their Committee, without the Preſence or Approbation of ſome of the Nobility, and ſome of the firſt Magnitude conſulted.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50986:17"/>
               <p>Perhaps <hi>others hath given in Propoſals to the King;</hi> perhaps <hi>the Pretenſions of the Vindicator are as good as any Mans of them all, perhaps better:</hi> I am a ſtranger to the Perſons of the one ſide, and to all Merits on the other, and therefore can ſay nothing. But this is clearly viſible, that this Paragraph was prolonged, only that in the Fag-end of it, we might be told, <hi>That he was known to our preſent King in</hi> Holland, <hi>attended him in his Expedition for</hi> England, <hi>and has Acceſs to him here;</hi> and this with an inſulting Glance at <hi>ſome few of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Gentlemen, who know few of their own Countrymen, more than what they meet at an Aſſizes;</hi> when his Converſation is at the Courts of Kings, and his Diverſion in the Cloſets of Princes.</p>
               <p>Nay the very <hi>Diſtribution of the Brief-money</hi> cannot eſcape his Cenſure. In his Opinion, it had been laid out to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſe, if <hi>imployd</hi> in the maintenance of <hi>his Project.</hi> Upon the next occaſion, I hope he will imploy his Intereſt to be made the Kings <hi>Almoner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now irritated by his own waſpiſh Diſpoſition, he falls fowl upon Sir <hi>St. J. Br—ck;</hi> a Gentleman, whom an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of many years hath render'd very well known to me, and no way deſerving thoſe black Characters fixt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in that ſcurrillous Pamphlet. And becauſe I am convinced, that he ſuffers under thoſe opprobrious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, meerly for his warmth and concernment for the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> I hold my ſelf obliged to ſtruggle in his Vindication, as far as my own knowledge of him will conduct me. And becauſe ſome officious Perſon may have traduced this Gentleman, (by whiſpering to the Projector, <hi>that his Propoſal was defamed by the other, with the Epithet of diſhoneſt and knaviſh;</hi> which is not likely to proceed from a Perſon of his Prudence and Temper) the Vindicator has adventured under his own Hand, to publiſh to the World, <hi>that Sir R. B. is guilty of Knavery, Inſolence, and Folly. Durus Sermo!</hi> This is Language fitter for <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> and deſerves an Anſwer more ſevere, than is proper for me to uſe. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I ſhall endeavour to be his Advocate, as far as my experience of him and his Actions will warrant me. And paſſing over the Calumny he placeth on the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>(that he has kept luſty young Men, that would have gone
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50986:18"/>over with our Army, theſe five Months in Pay upon the Brief-Money; that he has promiſed to carry over a hundred of them as Cadets; that the King will be deceived in relying on him</hi>) the improbability of which may juſtly ſuperſede all labour of Confutation, by a blunt Declaration that it is not ſo: I ſhall only ſay, that I have not obſerved a Gentleman more injuriouſly treated, nor more undeſervedly. And becauſe (according to his Method) he has ſqueeſed in an Occaſion to celebrate <hi>the great Author of a late excellent Treatiſe, called the Character of the Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland: I begin to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in my ſuſpicion, that the Author of the <hi>Propoſal</hi> and of the <hi>Character,</hi> is one and the ſame: (notwithſtanding that there is a great Diſparity in the Style and Deſign of thoſe two Papers, as well as in the Humour) had not the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithet of <hi>great,</hi> not properly applicable to him undeceived me.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman (whom the Vindicator caluminates) is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſixty years of Age; had the Character of a Colonel forty years ago; has been ſetled in <hi>England</hi> for Fifteen years paſt; what Temptations could prevail with him to forego his Quiet and Retirement, and expoſe his Life to imminent danger? I am ſatisfied, that his Undertaking was truly ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, prompted by Zeal to his Religion and Country; propoſing to himſelf a requital only in the futurity of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benters, and putting <hi>England</hi> to little or no Charge for his preſent Pay. And if by his care, and Charity (which has appeared univerſal to all the diſtreſſed Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi>) he procured a ſmall and temporary Relief for <hi>luſty young Men,</hi> as well as others; he is very ill requited by ſuch a Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſm, as if he had <hi>kept them in Pay by the Brief-Money, and ſo cheated Widows and Children of the Common Charity.</hi> What his Behaviour was in the time of the <hi>late King,</hi> I am not privy to; but this I will ſay, that if he did truckle to the Idols of thoſe Times, he is the moſt alter'd Man in the World: I have known him theſe many years a ſtout ſtickler for the Proteſtants, and their Intereſt, and on that Account mightily envy'd, hated, and threatned by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. But let the Truth of theſe Scandals be meaſured by his next Aſſertion, where he confidently ſays, <hi>This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man propoſed in the Committee, that the Fifteen thouſand Pounds might be applyed to the raiſing of his Regiment, and mounting
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50986:18"/>them;</hi> when it is notoriouſly known to all of that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, that there never was the leaſt Motion to any ſuch Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe made among them.</p>
               <p>And if before the Kings pleaſure were known, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly informed himſelf, whether he might rely on a certain Number of Men, to compoſe a Regiment, or a good part of it; I think it was but common Prudence in him, to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of that before he undertook it to the King, leaſt his <hi>Propoſal</hi> might prove as impracticable as that of the <hi>Projector.</hi> And when he demanded forfeited Lands, in lieu of preſent, and growing Pay; it was at his peril to loſe the ſatisfaction, <hi>if they did not deſerve it,</hi> and the King could run no Riſque by it.</p>
               <p>And now if the <hi>Vindicator will put himſelf into the Balance with this Gentleman,</hi> he muſt <hi>forgive me if I ſay,</hi> it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern him to caſt in ſome viſible Trumpery, beſide the airy weight of his Reputation; elſe it is eaſie to gueſs on which ſide the Scale will turn. But let any one judg, whether that Man be not ſcurrillous, that ſhall (without the leaſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Reaſon) ſay of a Gentleman, <hi>that he provokes even Clergymen to beat him?</hi> As I heartily wiſh the Propoſal of the Projector may not <hi>make him any thing;</hi> ſo I agree with him in Opinion, that he is <hi>unable to execute the Treaſurers Place, and unqualify'd for it;</hi> though at the ſame time he may fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy himſelf big enough to fill the Place of <hi>Principal Secretary of State,</hi> or ſome other great Employment, where Profit may be had without Danger: It is an ungentile Humour to make Compariſons; and though the Projectors <hi>Eſtate be ſetled, and has laſted for four Generations paſt,</hi> (which perhaps ſome Men do wonder at) what need was there to ſay, that <hi>he got none by perjuring himſelf, or other men; is not that a tacit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on</hi> Sir <hi>S. B.</hi> as if he had gotten his by ſuch means?</p>
               <p>I would fain know if Two Gentlemen, having handſom Wives, ſhould fall into a Debate about their Honeſty, and one of them ſhould ſay, my Wife is a handſom Woman, but I am no Cuckold, would not the other preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that he meant and reflected upon him? But the Eſtate of Sir <hi>S. B.</hi> it is well known was honeſtly gotten, by the meer dint of Induſtry, and moſt of it at ſixteen Years Purchaſe, after the Court of Claims was
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:50986:19"/>
               <p>But will you quarrel, Sir, becauſe they would not give you <hi>admittance among them, when they were drawing their Anſwer?</hi> Is that a uſual way among Antagoniſts? why you know, that formerly as ſoon as you <hi>entred the Room where they were reading it, the Reader was ſtruck ſilent, they were aſhamed to read any more, till you were gone:</hi> and would you have them run into the ſame Error again? Alaſs! the Fancy can never operate clearly, when the mind is awed by the Preſence of a Superiour Aſcendent. This Eſſay proves your Conjecture right, That <hi>ſome of us do make that uſe of the leiſure we have by our Exile, to anſwer every new Pamphlet, that does not ſuit with our own Notion:</hi> So that if you think fit to retract your Reſolution, and put out a <hi>Reply,</hi> I ſhall hope to find leiſure to furniſh a <hi>Rejoynder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time let it be obſerved, that when your firſt Paper was decry'd, you had leiſure to alter your Senſe in the ſecond: and when both were confuted by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Committee; you had then opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them both, and publiſh your laſt Model without the Errata's in the former.</p>
               <p>The reſt is but a Repitition or Comment upon his former Diſcourſes, inſiſting upon the <hi>ſowing of Corn, the Diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Money, the approbation of the King and Council,</hi> &amp;c. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſuperadds on irreſiſtible Incouragement to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, that <hi>he has declared his Purpoſe of going along, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing to the utmoſt of his Ability whatever hardſhips we ſhall meet with.</hi> And who would be ſo hard-hearted and ſo ſtupid, to refuſe to go under the Conduct of ſuch a Leader? or baulk any Hardſhip in the Society of ſuch a Companion in Miſery.</p>
               <p>The Paper concludes with a ſcornful ſide-look upon all the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who do not concur with his Senſe and Notions, as having <hi>forfeited His Majeſties Favour</hi> (which if any did ſuſpect before, they knew no reaſon for it till now) to which there is <hi>no poſſiblity of being reſtored, but by an humble Supplication to his Majeſty,</hi> &amp;c. joyning with the <hi>worthy</hi> Iriſh <hi>Gentry of</hi> Leverpool, whom they may find in the Perſon, or at the Lodgings of one <hi>R. T.</hi> And by this it ſeems, that the Author of it not only had the Honour <hi>to be known to our preſent King in</hi> Holland, <hi>and to attend him in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50986:19"/>his Expedition for</hi> England (when if <hi>there were not two more of</hi> Ireland <hi>to be ſeen,</hi> he means <hi>two more ſuch as himſelf) and to have acceſs to him here,</hi> but would make us believe, that he is acquainted with the Kings Mind, and knows the very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that may capacitate us to be <hi>Partakers of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that has imbroyl'd the Kings Affairs, and retarded the ſwift-winged Succeſs of his Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> is bound to ask the <hi>Kings Pardon;</hi> and ſo is the Author of the <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and not only ſo, but to crave Pardon of all the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland, the Nobility, Gentry, Lawyers, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornies, Solicitors, Clerks,</hi> &amp;c. and all whom he terms <hi>a Rabble.</hi> But if he be not ſo ingenious as to publiſh his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe in a penitential Sheet, I mightily dread his Fate, which if it prove unhappy, he muſt only thank himſelf for it.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50986:20"/>
            <head>Lately Printed,</head>
            <p>A <hi>Juſt and modeſt Vindication of the Proteſtants of</hi> Ireland, <hi>with Reflections on a late Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, Intituled</hi> The Character of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir</hi> St. John Broderick<hi>'s Vindication of himſelf, from the Aſperſions caſt on him, in a Pamphlet writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Sir</hi> Richard Buckley, <hi>Intituled,</hi> The Propoſals for ſending back the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with a Vindication of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
